What an intriguing group of individuals you are ...
يا لكم من مجموعة أفراد مثيرين
to a psychologist.
في نظر عالم نفسيّ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I've had the opportunity over the last couple of days
لقد أتيحت لي الفرصة على مدى اليومين الماضيين
of listening in on some of your conversations
للاستماع إلى بعض محادثاتكم
and watching you interact with each other.
ومشاهدتكم تتفاعلون مع بعضكم البعض
And I think it's fair to say, already,
وأعتقد بأنه من المنصف القول بالفعل
that there are 47 people in this audience,
أن 47 شخص من الجمهور
at this moment,
في هذه اللحظة
displaying psychological symptoms I would like to discuss today.
يظهرون أعراضًا نفسية أودّ مناقشتها اليوم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I thought you might like to know who you are.
وأعتقد أنكم تودون أن تعلموا من أنتم.
But instead of pointing at you,
ولكن بدلًا من أن أشير إليكم
which would be gratuitous and intrusive,
الأمرالذي سيكون لا مبرر له وتطفليّ
I thought I would tell you a few facts and stories,
أعتقد بأنّي سأخبركم ببعض الحقائق والقصص
in which you may catch a glimpse of yourself.
والتي من خلالها ستتمكنون من التقاط لمحات عنكم.
I'm in the field of research known as personality psychology,
أنا منخرط في مجال الأبحاث المعروفة باسم علم نفس الشخصية
which is part of a larger personality science
وهي جزء من علم النفس الأوسع
which spans the full spectrum, from neurons to narratives.
الذي يشمل الطيف الأوسع من النهايات العصبية إلى القصص الشخصية.
And what we try to do,
وما نحاول فعله
in our own way,
بطريقتنا الخاصة
is to make sense of how each of us --
هو لفهم كيف أنّ كل شخص منا
each of you --
كل شخص منكم
is, in certain respects,
هو من بعض النواحي
like all other people,
مثل كل الأشخاص
like some other people
مثل بعض الأشخاص
and like no other person.
ولا يشبه أيّ شخص آخر.
Now, already you may be saying of yourself,
الآن بالتأكيد ربما تقولون لأنفسكم
"I'm not intriguing.
"أنا شخص مثير
I am the 46th most boring person in the Western Hemisphere."
أنا في السادسة والأربعين أكثر شخص ممل في نصف الكرة الغربية"
Or you may say of yourself,
أو ربما تقولون لأنفسكم
"I am intriguing,
"أنا شخص مثير
even if I am regarded by most people as a great, thundering twit."
أنا الذي يعتبره أغلب الناس أكثرالأشخاص إثارة للسخرية".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it is your self-diagnosed boringness and your inherent "twitiness"
ولكنها حالة الملل التي شخصتموها أنتم والسخرية الكامنة داخلكم
that makes me, as a psychologist, really fascinated by you.
تجعلني كوني طبيب نفسي مفتون حقًا بكم.
So let me explain why this is so.
لذا دعوني أفسر لماذا يحدث هذا.
One of the most influential approaches in personality science
واحدة من الطرق الأكثر تأثيرًا في علم الشخصية
is known as trait psychology,
تعرف بعلم نفس السمة
and it aligns you along five dimensions which are normally distributed,
يقوم هذا العلم بدراستكم من خلال أبعاد خمسة توزّع بشكل طبيعي
and that describe universally held aspects of difference between people.
ويصف نواحي الفوارق ما بين الأشخاص.
They spell out the acronym OCEAN.
يختصرون هذا العلم بكلمة (OCEAN).
So, "O" stands for "open to experience,"
الحرف الأول "O" يرمز إلى "منفتح على التجربة"
versus those who are more closed.
بالمقارنة مع أولئك الأكثر انغلاقًا.
"C" stands for "conscientiousness,"
حرف "C" يرمز إلى"الوعي"
in contrast to those with a more lackadaisical approach to life.
على نقيض أولئك ذوو الطريقة المتكاسلة في الحياة.
"E" -- "extroversion," in contrast to more introverted people.
حرف "E" يرمز إلى"الانبساط" على نقيض الأشخاص الأكثر انطوائية.
"A" -- "agreeable individuals,"
حرف "A" يرمز إلى "الأشخاص الموافقين"
in contrast to those decidedly not agreeable.
على النقيض من أولئك الذين قرروا أن يكونوا غير موافقين.
And "N" -- "neurotic individuals,"
ويرمز حرف "N" إلى المضطربين عصبيًا
in contrast to those who are more stable.
على نقيض أولئك الأكثر اتزانًا.
All of these dimensions have implications for our well-being,
كل من هذه الأبعاد له آثارعلى طريقة عيشنا
for how our life goes.
على مسار حياتنا.
And so we know that, for example,
وإذًا نحن نعلم على سبيل المثال
openness and conscientiousness are very good predictors of life success,
الانفتاح والضميرمنبئات فعّالة للنجاح في الحياة
but the open people achieve that success through being audacious
ولكن الأشخاص المنفتحون يحققون النجاح عن طريق جرأتهم
and, occasionally, odd.
وأحيانًا الفردية.
The conscientious people achieve it through sticking to deadlines,
وأصحاب الضمائر الحية يحققون ذلك من خلال الالتزام بالمواعيد
to persevering, as well as having some passion.
والمثابرة وكذلك وجود بعض العاطفة.
Extroversion and agreeableness are both conducive
ويفضي كل من الانبساط والقبول
to working well with people.
للعمل بشكل جيد مع الناس.
Extroverts, for example, I find intriguing.
أنا على سبيل المثال أجد المنفتحين مثييرين للاهتمام
With my classes, I sometimes give them a basic fact
خلال صفوفي أحيانًا أعطيهم حقيقة أساسية
that might be revealing with respect to their personality:
يمكن أن تكشف أمورًا تتعلق بشخصيتهم
I tell them that it is virtually impossible for adults
أخبرهم أنه من المستحيل فرضيًا بالنسبة للبالغين
to lick the outside of their own elbow.
لعق الجانب الخارجي من الكوع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Did you know that?
هل تعلمون هذه الحقيقة؟
Already, some of you have tried to lick the outside of your own elbow.
حاول البعض منكم فعلًا أن يلعق الجانب الخارجي من كوعهم.
But extroverts amongst you
ولكن المنفتحين منكم
are probably those who have not only tried,
على الأرجح لم يحاولوا فقط ذلك
but they have successfully licked the elbow
بل إنهم نجحوا في لعق كوع
of the person sitting next to them.
الشخص الجالس قربهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Those are the extroverts.
هؤلاء هم المنفتحون.
Let me deal in a bit more detail with extroversion,
دعوني أتحدث بالتفصيل عن الانفتاحية
because it's consequential and it's intriguing,
لأنها تبعية ومثيرة للاهتمام
and it helps us understand what I call our three natures.
وتساعدنا في فهم ما أدعوه طبائعنا الثلاث.
First, our biogenic nature -- our neurophysiology.
أولًا طبيعتنا الأحيائية علم وظائف الأعصاب خاصتنا
Second, our sociogenic or second nature,
ثانيًا الاجتماعية أو الطبيعة الثانية
which has to do with the cultural and social aspects of our lives.
والتي تتعلق بالجوانب الثقافية والاجتماعية لحياتنا
And third, what makes you individually you -- idiosyncratic --
وثالثًا الطبيعة التي تجعلكم متفردبن الطبيعة الفردية
what I call your "idiogenic" nature.
واتي أدعوها طبيعة التفرّد
Let me explain.
دعوني أشرح ذلك.
One of the things that characterizes extroverts is they need stimulation.
واحدة من الأشياء التي تميز المنفتحون هي أنهم يحتاجون التحفيز
And that stimulation can be achieved by finding things that are exciting:
ويمكن الوصول إلى هذا التحفيز عند إيجاد أمر مثير
loud noises, parties and social events here at TED --
الأصوات الصاخبة والحفلات والأحداث الاجتماعية هنا في TED
you see the extroverts forming a magnetic core.
يشكل المنفتحون نواةً مغناطيسية.
They all gather together.
يجتمعون مع بعضهم البعض
And I've seen you.
ولقد لاحظتكم
The introverts are more likely to spend time in the quiet spaces
ويفضّل الانطوائيون على الأرجع قضاء الوقت في الأماكن الهادئة
up on the second floor,
في الطابق الأعلى
where they are able to reduce stimulation --
حيث يكونون قادرين على الحد من التحفيز
and may be misconstrued as being antisocial,
ويمكن أن يساء فهمهم على أنهم معادين للمجتمع
but you're not necessarily antisocial.
ليس بالضرورة أن تكونوا معادين للمجتمع.
It may be that you simply realize that you do better
بل ربما تدركون بأنكم تؤدون بشكل أفضل
when you have a chance to lower that level of stimulation.
عندما تسنح لكم الفرص بخفض مستوى التحفيز
Sometimes it's an internal stimulant, from your body.
أحيانًا يكون المحفز داخليًا من داخل جسدكم.
Caffeine, for example, works much better with extroverts than it does introverts.
على سبيل المثال يؤثر الكافيين أكثر بالمنفتحين من تأثيره على الانطوائيين
When extroverts come into the office at nine o'clock in the morning
عندما يصل المنفتحون إلى مكاتبهم في الساعة التاسعة صباحًا
and say, "I really need a cup of coffee,"
ويقولون"أحتاج حقًا إلى فنجان قهوة"
they're not kidding --
هم لا يمزحون
they really do.
بالفعل هم بحاجة القهوة.
Introverts do not do as well,
لا يقوم الانطوائيون بهذا
particularly if the tasks they're engaged in --
لاسيما إذا كانت المهام الموكلة إليهم
and they've had some coffee --
وهم قد احتسوا قهوتهم
if those tasks are speeded,
وتسارعت تلك المهام
and if they're quantitative,
فإذا كانوا كميّين
introverts may give the appearance of not being particularly quantitative.
ربما لا يعطي الانطوائيون انطباعًا بأنهم كميّون على وجه الخصوص
But it's a misconstrual.
ولكن هذا ما يساء فهمه.
So here are the consequences that are really quite intriguing:
إذًا هذه هي العواقب المثيرة للاهتمام حقيقةً
we're not always what seem to be,
لسنا دائمًا بالشكل الذي نبدو عليه
and that takes me to my next point.
وهذا يفضي بي إلى النقطة التالية.
I should say, before getting to this,
يجب عليّ التحدث قبل الخوض بهذه النقطة
something about sexual intercourse,
بأمر يخصّ الاتصال الجنسيّ
although I may not have time.
على الرغم من أنّي أفتقر للوقت الكافي.
And so, if you would like me to --
إلا إذا أردتم منّي الحديث
yes, you would?
نعم أنتم تريدون
OK.
حسنًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There are studies done
هناك دراسات قامت
on the frequency with which individuals engage in the conjugal act,
حول الوتيرة التي يقوم بها الأفراد بالعلاقة الزوجية
as broken down by male, female; introvert, extrovert.
كما يتمّ تصنيفها بعلاقة الذكروالأنثى المنفتح والمنطوي
So I ask you:
لذلك أوجّه السؤال لكم:
How many times per minute --
كم مرة في الدقيقة
oh, I'm sorry, that was a rat study --
أعتذر تلك دراسة تخصّ الجرذان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How many times per month
كم مرة في الشهر
do introverted men engage in the act?
هل ينخرط الرجال الاننطوائيون بالعمل؟
Extroverted men?
ماذا عن الرجال المنفتحين؟
More or less?
أكثر أم أقل؟
Yes, more.
نعم أكثر
5.5 -- almost twice as much.
5.5 تقريبًا الضعف
Introverted women: 3.1.
النساء الانطوائيات 3.1
Extroverted women?
ماذا عن النساء المنفتحات؟
Frankly, speaking as an introverted male,
بصراحة، بالحديث بلسان ذكر انطوائي
which I will explain later --
وهذا ما سأفسره لاحقًا
they are heroic.
هم أبطال
7.5.
7.5
They not only handle all the male extroverts,
هم لايتعاملون فقط مع الذكور المنفتحين
they pick up a few introverts as well.
بل ينتقون بعض الانطوائيين أيضًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We communicate differently, extroverts and introverts.
نتواصل بشكل مختلف أقصد المنفتحين والانطوائيين.
Extroverts, when they interact,
فعندما يتفاعل المنفتحون
want to have lots of social encounter punctuated by closeness.
يرغبون بقدركبيرمن المواجهة الاجتماعية يتخللها التقارب.
They'd like to stand close for comfortable communication.
يرغبون في البقاء بمقربة اتصال مريح.
They like to have a lot of eye contact,
يحلو لهم الكثيرمن التواصل البصري
or mutual gaze.
أو النظرات المتبادلة.
We found in some research
ما وجدناه في بعض الأبحاث
that they use more diminutive terms when they meet somebody.
أنّهم يستخدمون مصطلحات تصغيرية عندما يجتمعون مع شخص ما.
So when an extrovert meets a Charles,
لذلك في حال قابل منفتح أحداً يدعى "تشارلز"
it rapidly becomes "Charlie," and then "Chuck,"
سيغدو بسرعة "تشارلي" وثم "تشاك"
and then "Chuckles Baby."
وثم "حبيبي تشاكلس"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Whereas for introverts,
أما بالنسبة للانطوائيين
it remains "Charles," until he's given a pass to be more intimate
يبقى الاسم"تشرلز" حتى يعطى الإذن بأن يكون حميميًا أكثر
by the person he's talking to.
من قبل الشخص الذي يتحدث معه.
We speak differently.
نحن نتحدث بشكل مختلف.
Extroverts prefer black-and-white, concrete, simple language.
يفضّل المنفتحون الأبيض والأسود والأمور الملموسة واللغة البسيطة.
Introverts prefer -- and I must again tell you
ويفضّل الانطوائيون ويجب عليي أن أخبركم مجددًا
that I am as extreme an introvert as you could possibly imagine --
بأنني أكثر انطوائيّ يمكن أن تتخيلوه
we speak differently.
نتحدث بشكل مختلف.
We prefer contextually complex,
نفضّل نحن السياق المعقد
contingent,
المصادفة
weasel-word sentences --
الجمل بالكلمات المراوغة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
More or less.
أكثر أو أقل
As it were.
كما كانت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not to put too fine a point upon it --
دون وضع نقاط أكثر دقّة على جملنا
like that.
مثل ذلك.
When we talk,
عندما نتحدث
we sometimes talk past each other.
أحيانًا تتداخل أحاديثنا.
I had a consulting contract I shared with a colleague
كان لدي عقد استشاري تشاركته مع أحد زملائي
who's as different from me as two people can possibly be.
وهو مختلف عنّي إلى حد كبير
First, his name is Tom.
أولًا يدعى توم
Mine isn't.
أمّا أنا لا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Secondly, he's six foot five.
ثانيًا يبلغ طوله ستة أقدام ونصف
I have a tendency not to be.
أما أنا لديّ الرغبة بأن لا أكون بهذا الطول
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And thirdly, he's as extroverted a person as you could find.
وثالثًا هو أكثر شخص منفتح يمكن أن تلتقوه
I am seriously introverted.
أما أنا انطوائي بحقّ.
I overload so much,
أنا أحمّل نفسي أكثر من طاقتها
I can't even have a cup of coffee after three in the afternoon
حتى أنّي لو أحتسيت فنجان قهوة بعد الثالثة عصرًا
and expect to sleep in the evening.
لا أقدر على النوم مساءً.
We had seconded to this project a fellow called Michael.
انتدبنا لهذا المشروع زميلًا يدعى مايكل
And Michael almost brought the project to a crashing halt.
وكاد مايكل أن يفشل المشروع.
So the person who seconded him asked Tom and me,
لذلك توجه الشخص الذي انتدبه بالسؤال إليّ وإلى توم
"What do you make of Michael?"
"ما رأيكم بمايكل؟"
Well, I'll tell you what Tom said in a minute.
سأخبركم بردّ توم بعد قليل.
He spoke in classic "extrovert-ese."
تحدث بلغة المنفتحين التقليدية
And here is how extroverted ears heard what I said,
وبهذا الشكل تستمع أذن المنفتحين لما قلته
which is actually pretty accurate.
وهو حقيقةً أمر دقيق جدًا
I said, "Well Michael does have a tendency at times
قلت:" حسنًا إنّ لمايكل هذه النزعة في أوقات محددة
of behaving in a way that some of us might see
للتصرف بأسلوب قد يراه البعض منا
as perhaps more assertive than is normally called for."
ربما أكثر حزمًا مما يستدعيه الأمر بشكل طبيعي".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Tom rolled his eyes and he said,
نظ توم باستغراب وقال
"Brian, that's what I said:
"هذا ما قلته تمامًا برايان"
he's an asshole!"
"إنّه أحمق"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, as an introvert,
الآن، كوني انطوائيًا
I might gently allude to certain "assholic" qualities
ربما أشير بلطف إلى بعض صفات الحماقة
in this man's behavior,
في سلوك هذا الشخص
but I'm not going to lunge for the a-word.
ولكني لن أندفع وأنطق تلك الكلمة التي تبدأ بحرف (أ).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the extrovert says,
ولكن المنفتحين يقولون
"If he walks like one, if he talks like one, I call him one."
"إذا تحدث مثل واحد وتكلم مثل واحد سأدعوه واحد"
And we go past each other.
ونحن نسبق بعضنا البعض.
Now is this something that we should be heedful of?
هل يجب أن نكترث لهذا الأمر؟
Of course.
طبعاً.
It's important that we know this.
إنّه من المهم أن نعلم هذا
Is that all we are?
هل هذا كل شيء عنّا؟
Are we just a bunch of traits?
هل نحن فقط عبارة عن مجموعة من الصفات؟
No, we're not.
لا، نحن لسنا كذلك.
Remember, you're like some other people
تذكروا أنكم تشبهون أشخاصًا آخرين
and like no other person.
ولكنكم أيضًا فريدون.
How about that idiosyncratic you?
ماذا عن خاصيتك الفردية تلك؟
As Elizabeth or as George,
كما إليزابيث أو جورج
you may share your extroversion or your neuroticism.
من الممكن أن تشارك انفتاحك أو عصبيتك.
But are there some distinctively Elizabethan features of your behavior,
ولكن هل هناك بعض الملامح الإليزابيثية التي تميّز سلوكك
or Georgian of yours,
أو ملامح جورجية
that make us understand you better than just a bunch of traits?
هذا يجعلنا نفهمك أكثر من كونك مجموعة من الصفات؟
That make us love you?
هذا يجعلنا نحبك؟
Not just because you're a certain type of person.
ليس لأنك فقط نمط خاص من الأشخاص.
I'm uncomfortable putting people in pigeonholes.
لا أرتاح حين أفرز الأشخاص في صناديق الحمام.
I don't even think pigeons belong in pigeonholes.
حتى أني لا أعتقد أن الحمام ينتمي إلى تلك الصناديق
So what is it that makes us different?
إذًا ما الذي يجعلنا مختلفين؟
It's the doings that we have in our life -- the personal projects.
إنه ما نقوم به من أفعال مشاريعنا الشخصية
You have a personal project right now,
لديكم حاليًا مشاريع شخصية
but nobody may know it here.
ولكن قد لا يعلمها أحد.
It relates to your kid --
هي تخصّك أيها الصغير
you've been back three times to the hospital,
ذهبت إلى المشفى ثلاث مرات حتى الآن
and they still don't know what's wrong.
ومازالوا لا يعلمون ما خطبك.
Or it could be your mom.
قد تكون والدتك.
And you'd been acting out of character.
وكنت تتصرف انطلاقًا من شخصيتك
These are free traits.
هذه هي الصفات الحرة.
You're very agreeable, but you act disagreeably
أنت مستعد للموافقة ولكنك تتصرف بطريقة الرفض
in order to break down those barriers of administrative torpor
من أجل كسر تلك الحواجز من السبات الإداري
in the hospital,
في المشفى
to get something for your mom or your child.
لتحصل على شيء لأمك أو لطفلك.
What are these free traits?
ما هي تلك الصفات الحرة؟
They're where we enact a script
إنها تلك التي استخدمناها لكتابة النص
in order to advance a core project in our lives.
من أجل المضيّ قدمًا في مشروع حياتنا الأساسي.
And they are what matters.
وهي تحديدًا ما يهمنا.
Don't ask people what type you are;
لا تسأل الناس من أيّ نمط أنتم
ask them, "What are your core projects in your life?"
اسألهم: "ما هو مشروع حياتكم الأساسي؟"
And we enact those free traits.
ونحن نكتب تلك الصفات الحرة.
I'm an introvert,
أنا انطوائي
but I have a core project, which is to profess.
ولكن لدي مشروع أساسي وهو أن أدرّس
I'm a professor.
أنا مدرّس.
And I adore my students,
وأنا أعشق طلابي
and I adore my field.
وأعشق اختصاصي.
And I can't wait to tell them about what's new, what's exciting,
ولا يسعني الانتظارلإخبارهم بكل أمر جديد ومشوّق
what I can't wait to tell them about.
بكل الأمور التي لايسعني انتظار إخبارهم بها
And so I act in an extroverted way,
لذلك أتصرف بطريقة انفتاحية
because at eight in the morning,
لأنه في الساعة الثامنة صباحًا
the students need a little bit of humor,
يحتاج الطلاب لشيء من حسّ الدعابة
a little bit of engagement to keep them going
لشيء يدفعهم للمضيّ قدماً
in arduous days of study.
في أيام الدراسة الشاقة.
But we need to be very careful
ولكن علينا الحذر
when we act protractedly out of character.
عندما نتصرف لمدة طويلة بصورة خارجة عن طبيعتنا.
Sometimes we may find that we don't take care of ourselves.
يمكن أحيانًا أن نكتشف بأننا مقصرين بحقّ أنفسنا
I find, for example, after a period of pseudo-extroverted behavior,
على سبيل المثال، اكتشفت أنه وبعد فترة من سلوك شبه انفتاحي
I need to repair somewhere on my own.
أنه عليّ إصلاح أمرما داخلي.
As Susan Cain said in her "Quiet" book,
كا قالت سوزان كين في كتابها"الصمت"
in a chapter that featured the strange Canadian professor
في أحد فصوله الذي وصف البروفيسو الكندي الغريب
who was teaching at the time at Harvard,
الذي كان يدرس في تلك الفترة في هارفارد
I sometimes go to the men's room
أذهب أحيانًا إلى حمام الرجال
to escape the slings and arrows of outrageous extroverts.
هربًا من صعوبات وشدائد المنفتحين المشينين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I remember one particular day when I was retired to a cubicle,
أتذكر في أحد الأيام ذهبت لأستريح في الحمام
trying to avoid overstimulation.
في محاولة لتجنب التنبيه المفرط.
And a real extrovert came in beside me -- not right in my cubicle,
وجاء شخص منفتح بحقّ إلى جانبي ليس داخل ذات المقصورة
but in the next cubicle over --
ولكن داخل المقصورة بجانبي
and I could hear various evacuatory noises,
سمعت مختلف أصوات التفريغ
which we hate -- even our own,
التي نكرهها، حتى التي تخصّنا
that's why we flush during as well as after.
لذلك نستخدم الماء أثناء وبعد التفريغ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then I heard this gravelly voice saying,
ثم سمعت صوتًا أجشًا يقول
"Hey, is that Dr. Little?"
"هل هذا الدكتور ليتل؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If anything is guaranteed to constipate an introvert for six months,
إذا كان هناك سبب يضمن حالة إمساك تصيب شخصًا انطوائيًا لمدة ستة أشهر
it's talking on the john.
فهو التحدث في دورة المياه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's where I'm going now.
إلى هناك أنا متوجه الآن
Don't follow me.
لا تلحقوا بي.
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)